All good.
OK, think we can get started.
Welcome back to this room.
We still have a lot of people.
That's good.
I like Thursdays.
It's almost full here.
OK, we're going to continue where we stopped last time, but today we're going to change gears a
little bit.
We've been covering digital design.
Now we're going to raise the abstraction level and talk about model of computing, and then we're
going to talk about how to implement that model of computing based on what you learnt.
But before we get there, there is your extra credit assignment.
The assignment due date is coming up.
Remember, no AI use.
And we have an extra lecture that I'm going to motivate right now that we're not going to cover.
We covered actually most of it in the last lecture, but there's some part that we didn't cover that
could be useful for your labs.
So we released a lecture for you.
This is what we covered in the last several lectures.
Remember, you covered combination logic, sequential logic circuits, and we talked about the timing
analysis of both in the last lecture, and we mostly covered whatever is written over here.
I'd like to emphasize that timing is really important because we'll have many sequential components
in a circuit.
And we discussed, for example, how to determine the clock cycle time, which is the maximum logic
delay across different possible paths within a sequential circuit.
And normally when you do timing analysis to decide the clock frequency of a processor, for example,
you need to do this analysis for every single timing path that exists.
And what is the timing path essentially between two different flip flops?
1 flip flop is the input, the other flip flop latches the output.
And you need to ensure that the operations are done within the clock cycle and you get the correct
result, including all of the issues that we discussed, including the confidential logic delay,
sequential logic delay, hold top hold time, setup time, clock skew, all of those things, plus wire
delays, which we did not talk about.
Those are also important.
So you need to find the maximum logic delay across all of the different sequential components that
you have in a system.
And that maximum logic delay is the limiter of your frequency.
OK.
So if you want a higher frequency processor, and we'll talk about the importance of frequency in
terms of performance later, in a later lecture, like lecture 9 or 10, you need to actually meet
these timing constraints.
So how you design A processor, you have a target frequency.
Let's say I want my processor to be fixed 50 gigahertz.
It's a bit tough today to do that, but it's possible in the near future, I think.
And that gives you a clock cycle time.
And you need to make sure every single timing path in your processor satisfies that 50 gigahertz
frequency.
And you can calculate how many nanoseconds that is this 1 / 50 gigahertz, right?
OK, so a clock cycle time is determined by that maximum logic delay.
We can accommodate without violating timing constraints.
And usually if you want to improve your clock cycle time, you can follow good design principles.
These will come later when we talk about micro architecture also, but we need to do a critical path
design, meaning minimise the maximum logic delay that exists in the entire processor.
First of all.
How do you figure that out?
Well, if you have trillion transistors, it becomes difficult to figure that out, but it's possible
and this maximises performance.
And if you want to do a critical path design later, we will see that you want to actually balance
the components as much as possible.
You have, let's say, millions of sequential logic components where you have one register as input
and another register as output, and there's some combination logic.
You want to balance the combinational logic delays as much as possible, as we will see in
pipelining, for example.
That's brings me to the balance design.
You balance maximum logic delays across different parts of a system, meaning between different pairs
of flip flops.
So hopefully you will have no bottlenecks.
Meaning one path should not be extremely long compared to all of the other paths, because then you
waste the time, right?
Because you determine your clock frequency globally and that's determined based on the maximum
delay.
But then there may be 100,000 different paths in your design that are much, much less than that.
That means that whenever you're using those other paths, you're wasting a lot of time because you
determine your clock frequency based on something else that took much longer.
We'll see this also in pipelining, and this is actually called balance design.
You really balance the timing paths across all of your design, which is not easy to achieve.
And to be able to do balance design, normally what you do is if you have a very long path between 2
flip flops, what you do is you divide it into two paths.
For example, insert a flip flop in between such that you have one flip flop input another flip.
Flop as output and that becomes the input of the other combination logic that you divide it into
two.
OK, That's the idea of pipelining actually.
OK.
And then there's the third component, which is also called common case design.
We call bread and butter design.
Basically, there's some bread and butter.
You're designing the system for use case.
What is the system going to execute?
You optimise for the common case.
You understand what the system is going to execute.
If it's machine learning workloads, basically you're doing a lot of matrix multiplications, then you
optimise your design to execute matrix multiplications fast and maybe treat the other parts that
are not executed as much such that they don't overwhelm the design.
So essentially this optimised the system for common use cases, and this can also be done for timing.
For example, there could be a really important instruction that you want to execute.
We'll talk about instructions today, and you optimise the timing path for that one.
And you execute some other instructions less fast, let's say, or more slowly.
And if that instruction occurs 99.99% of the time in your program, then you're actually optimising
for the common case.
The remaining parts may be executing slowly, but it doesn't occur that much, right?
So we'll see this more and more.
Also, this is also bringing us to Mdal's law.
It's actually Mdal's law, in the end, optimised for what's really important, right?
OK, so this is the final word on timing, but timing is not enough.
You need to make sure a design works directly.
That's why I would like you to watch the verification and testing.
And I would like to motivate a little bit more because verification and testing are actually getting
much worse today.
And there are two types of verification and testing.
As we discussed, functional and timing.
Functional in, in functional verification and testing, you're making sure that the circuit logically
operates correctly so there are no logical bugs, let's say, or logical problems.
This is a bit easier, still expensive, as you will see in the lecture if you watch it, timing is
much more, much more expensive and much more difficult.
Here you make sure the circuit operates correctly at the desired timing target.
You said my frequency should be 5 gigahertz.
So you need to make sure that the circuit operates under all conditions, all input conditions under
all programs at this at 5 gigahertz, let's say much more difficult.
And as a result of this verification and testing consume most of the manufacturing time, 70% cost
and time also time is also cost by the way, if you're, if you're really trying to push something
out to the market, if you're delayed, then somebody will push something else maybe subpar.
But if they actually are more timely, they can capture more of the market before you do.
OK.
So essentially verification and testing are performed at many stage of design.
You will see that you will do it in your labs pre silicon meaning before the silicon's manufactured,
and also post silicon after the silicon's manufactured.
There's a lot of testing and verification that happens to make sure that that silicon actually works
OK both functionally and timing wise.
In the end, it's very difficult to completely verify and test complex circuits, partly because the
scale is huge and also the input sizes are huge.
And also there are many operating conditions, right?
We discussed voltage, temperature at the beginning of last lecture, right?
Humidity.
If these change, the timing paths also change, right?
If you don't, if you haven't considered these things and put enough timing margin, or if you didn't
change your timing requirements or frequency clock frequency based on what happens environmentally,
you may run into a situation where under one condition your circuits works really well, but under
another condition it fails because even though it's functionally correct, because it fails timing
because at some high temperature it actually ran slowly for some reason, right?
It's good to think about that.
OK, so even after so much verification and testing, errors still slip into the field basically
today.
So if you're watching, for example, and doing the extra assignment, you will see that all DRAM chips
have a problem called raw hammer and raw press.
That's one example of data corruption, for example, that happens even after a lot of verification
and testing of memory.
And as a result, people have been developing online verification and testing methods.
So when the computer is actually operating, the system is testing itself.
So more and more these will happen.
I'll give you a couple of examples of this.
So memory you're watching, I'm going to mention that also soon, but there's also more recently
people at Google, Meta, Microsoft, Alibaba, they've shown that in their big fleets, sometimes they
get errors, meaning the computer is supposed to do some computation, but it gives the wrong result,
right?
And this basically messes up everything, including machine learning, training, inference, whatever
they're doing over there.
And a lot of these things that are these, these are called silent data corruptions.
So you get a data corruption for whatever reason and as a result the system fails or breaks or you
get a wrong result.
There could be many, many symptoms of it.
And these silent data corruptions are not desirable.
And people are shown that this happening in existing systems.
And even if one processor fails every, let's say 30 months, if you have hundreds of thousands of
processors, then you can do the calculations to figure out how many failures you get every day,
right?
It's a lot, actually.
In the end, you'll get a lot.
OK, so people have figured out that some of these are related to timing issues because under some
conditions you have some timing here.
I'm not going to read this.
You can read it on your own time.
Under some conditions, like some voltage fluctuation, that happens due to the power supply in the
processor, and because of that you get a voltage droop that's called.
And as a result, you don't have enough voltage supplied to the circuit and you assume the timing
based on some voltage level.
But now your voltage level doesn't hold based on your assumption.
And at that point you latch an incorrect result because you didn't have enough timing, enough time
to complete the calculation that you're trying to do right.
And once you latch an incorrect result into R2, remember R1R2 combination logic in between that may
propagate into everything in your program logic, right?
And that's what people have been seeing in the field.
And Raw Hammer is another example of it, which is a completely different thing, but it's still
silent data corruption.
And I'll let you watch the lecture.
I don't have time to cover it right now, but we're going to get back to it.
When we talk about virtual memory, there are a lot of memory issues.
So Raw Hammer is an older silent data corruption issue which we discovered now 12 years ago.
Actually, actually really 14 years ago, but we wrote the paper in 2014, OK.
So these issues can also be security issues, as you will see in the extra credit assignment if you
have some silent data corruption.
And if people figure out how to induce these corruptions, they can actually induce it carefully.
If they're malicious, they can actually induce it carefully such that they can take over your
system.
Again, I will not describe how to do that.
This will become more clear when we get to lecture 26, virtual memory.
That's the last lecture of the course, but it's fascinating that with this sort of silent data
corruption, someone can take over your system.
Someone can actually do a lot of different things.
I'm not going to do that, but you can see some of that in the lecture.
OK, so that's your extracted assignment.
That's why it's important.
So I'll put more, I'm putting this more into context right now of what we've learnt so far,
verification and testing.
And part of the reason that these errors or these silent data corruptions in memory slipped into the
field was it was very, very difficult to verify and test billions and billions of memory cells in a
chip to make sure under all conditions you don't get a silent data corruption problem like Row
Hammer.
And this is not the only problem.
There are many more problems that my group has discovered.
Otto Bark is sitting over there thinking of the next thing.
Maybe you can talk to him if you're interested, because he's discovered a couple of these.
OK.
So basically the big challenge and opportunity we have going into the future, there are many
challenges we have in computing system design.
How do we build fundamentally robust systems?
Robust is reliable, safe, secure, available, predictable.
And we need this more and more because technology is becoming smaller and the conditions under which
we're going to operate these systems is becoming larger and larger, right?
We're talking about robotics, robots doing things right.
If you don't make a robot robust, even if the intention of the robot is fine, meaning they don't
have a a malicious intent, it may be erroneous.
And that error, it's very difficult to distinguish between error and malice.
Basically, you may get an error and that error could be, could cause a reliability problem, but it
could also be a safety problem or a security problem essentially.
And we're talking about going to space, for example, people are talking about space data centres,
people are talking about going in space.
And those are very harsh conditions, right?
And we don't know a lot of those conditions.
And our systems are not built for those conditions, OK?
So verification and testing both offline and online are critical, essentially.
And you'll get a glimpse of it in your labs.
This may be the part that you dislike.
In fact, it's kind of a thing not to be liked, right?
At least everybody wants to design something new, right?
Not verify something that's old.
But this, that is a part that's really critical to ensure a system is working basically.
So innovating in this area is also very important.
Actually, one of the best ways of learning a system is designing techniques to verify that system.
You didn't design that system.
Let's say somebody threw that at you and your first job may be the verification engineer of that
particular.
It could be software, it could be hardware.
I think it applies both.
If you really want to learn the system, do a great job verifying it and you will probably learn that
system better than the person who designed it but didn't verify it.
Because verification actually requires some things doing some things that you may not think during
design, right?
OK, so please watch lecture 66C.
It will give you a very small overview of verification and testing approach and it's complexity and
it will have some examples of how to do testing in Verilogue, which you will do a lot in your labs.
So that's lecture succeed.
Any questions?
OK, now this brings me to the end of the digital design part of this course.
This is what we covered so far.
Essentially, we're mostly done with the digital design part of this course, although we're going to
use the knowledge that we got and the principles that we developed for later parts of the course.
So today and the next few lectures, and that's a lot of lectures actually today especially, we're
going to talk about the ISA.
So we're going to jump one level up the hardware software interface.
In fact, we're going to talk about execution model to begin with, and then we're going to develop
the hardware software interface to enable it later.
We're going to connect it to the logic because it's important to give the high level picture top
down first over here before we connect it to the logic structures.
Although I'm going to give you some example of how to connect it to the logic structures, but I'm
not going to construct the logic to execute the hardware software interface yet.
So this is what we're going to do actually.
Hopefully people are excited.
OK, so we're going to start with a model, and this is not going to be the only model you will see,
but this is the dominant model that we have, which is the von Neumann model.
People may have heard of John von Neumann.
He was a pioneer in computing, clearly.
And we're going to talk about the hardware, software interface that obeys the von Neumann model.
And then we're going to talk about some instructions.
Some of this is going to be kind of boring, but hopefully this is going to be important so that you
can appreciate how you would talk to a computer.
And then we're going to talk about assembly and programming, which you will do in some of your labs.
And then we're going to talk about how to implement these things in a lot more detail in next week
and then week after that and then week after that.
Sounds good.
OK, I see some heads nodding.
OK, so today we're going to talk about the basic elements of a computer von Neumann model.
So we're going to go a little bit higher up.
As I said, we're not going to talk about gates.
We're going to talk about instructions, how to construct it, how how does a computer execute things,
And then we're going to talk about the instructions that architectures.
I usually do this by following two different kinds of instructions that architectures.
MIPS is 1 architecture that is used in some embedded systems today, but it's also inspired a lot of
other architectures like RISC 5 for example, you may have heard of.
It's mostly MIPS basically, except it's an open source MIPS.
That's my very, let's say short summary of what RISC 5 is if you're interested.
Of course, because it's open source, it can evolve better.
But essentially MIPS is a real instructions that architecture that people have implemented for many
years.
They're still implementing it and it has inspired a lot of other architectures.
And we're going to talk about a toy architecture LC3.
It's nice and instructional because there is a nice implementation of it that we're going to study
because it's it has it has a limited set of instructions and we're going to look at fundamental
instructions, instruction formats, addressing modes, data types, etcetera.
Sounds good, right?
OK, so this is some readings that you can use to supplement these lectures.
And next week we're going to start how to implement the instructions at architecture, which is
called micro architecture.
OK, so let's start with the von Neumann model.
But before we do that, let's start with how do you build a computing system, right?
So what is a computer?
That's a very fundamental question, right?
So essentially modern computers consist of three major structures.
As I've said some time ago, you have some processing mechanisms that consist of both data path and
control.
We're going to define these more and more clearly as we go into especially micro architecture and
you have some memory that stores both program and data that you're operating on.
And you have some communication mechanisms called IO or interconnects at every point.
Actually inside the processing, you have some communication mechanism like wires.
We've seen you have some wires connecting processing and memory.
You have some wires connecting memory and other components.
So interconnect is actually everywhere inside a computing system.
And we're going to see that, although we're not going to have a very explicit lecture on
interconnects, even though it's such a critical component.
OK, So we're going to start especially with processing, but in the past lecture.
We've learnt how to design combination logic, sequential logic, we've learnt how to verify and test
them.
Hopefully with these, we built an ALU, for example, that's an execution unit, right?
We're going to build more of these, right?
At least assume that they could be buildable, right?
With everything that you've seen, you should be able to build anything right now, right?
If you're given a very complicated polynomial evaluation or division algorithm, you should be able
to do it with NAND gates.
It may not be efficient, but you could do it right.
We're going to build also decision units, memory and storage units and communication units and all
our basic elements of a computer.
And we'll raise our abstraction level today.
As I said, go to the interface over here.
And to be able to do that, we need to define a computing model.
And then later, over time, we will use logic structures to realise this interface.
But I'm going to give you a glimpse of it today also when we go through instructions.
So essentially we want to build a computer, right?
Let's assume it's a general purpose computer, but the principles are very similar for accelerators.
Also.
We're going to talk about accelerators later on in this course for the purpose of this lecture and
in the next few lectures, next several lectures.
It's a general purpose computer.
It should be able to execute essentially every program that you throw at it, right?
To get a task done or to get a program executed, you need a program essentially clearly, that
specifies what the computer must do.
Right now, you've written these programs.
I'm sure everybody here has written programs in the first semester.
You're probably writing it right now also.
And the computer itself, right?
And the computer itself carries out the specified task.
So what is a program?
The program is, in the end, a set of instructions.
Each instruction specifies a well defined piece of work for the computer to carry out.
You guys agree?
Hopefully no contest over here.
Instruction is the smallest piece of specified work in a program.
An instruction set is all possible instructions that a computer is designed to be able to carry out.
That's what an instruction set is.
When when someone says what is the instruction set of this computer, it shouldn't come past all
possible instructions essentially that the computer is designed to be able to carry out.
OK with those definitions.
Let's talk about the von Neumann model.
So in order to build a computer, you need an execution model for processing computing programs,
right?
So you're given a set of instructions.
The question is, how do I process them, right?
If you're creative, you could come up with probably 1000 methods of processing them.
And people have done that.
And this is really the creative part of computing architecture.
Actually.
We need more ways of processing programs.
Von Neumann was both very smart and lucky, and he was early in the game, so he was able to come up
with a simple execution model that actually works really nicely in 1940s.
That's simple, and this is one of the works that summarises this paradigm.
So in von Neumann model, a computer has four, five components.
I'm going to actually just split down to two major things later on, which is going to be a stored
program and sequential execution.
These are the two hallmarks of von Neumann model, but we're going to get to that.
You have 5 components, memory that stores the program and data processing unit that executes it,
inputs, outputs and control units.
Control units controls the order in which instructions are carried out.
And in one normal model, sequential order, you execute 1 instruction and then you move to the next
one, and then you move to the next one, and then you move to the next one.
You don't execute the next instruction.
There's an order of instruction, which is program order or sequential order.
You don't reorder the instructions in any way.
OK, we're going to break that later on, OK, But in an interesting way, not completely break it.
You could completely break it.
Actually, we're going to do that also.
OK, throughout this lecture, we'll examine 2 examples of this von Neumann model, MIPS, NLC 3.
But keep in mind that essentially all instructions that architectures that we have that are dominant
today X86 for example, database, the von Neumann model ARM.
Another example, risk 5.
Risk 5 is kind of next generation MIPS, let's say.
OK, so all general purpose computers today use the von Neumann model.
So this is von Neumann model from one of your books, the Pat and Patel book.
You can see that these are the five components.
And we're going to look at these five components.
We're going to later focus a lot on the processing and control units and then in the later parts of
the course memory.
But there's also input and output that are important.
We're going to mention them, but we're not going to be able to look at input and output as much.
But they're also important, clearly.
OK, recall that this is a memory array essentially.
We all already talked a little bit about memory, but I'm going to go through this a little bit more
because there are some things that are important for addressing and also ordering of bytes, for
example.
So memory stores both programs and data.
This is going to be important.
Each memory location has some bits.
You could interpret any bit as program or data.
We will see that memory contains bits.
I said this.
This are logically grouped into bytes and words.
Bytes are 8 bits.
Words are.
Words are dependent on the architecture.
Instructions that architecture basically.
But nobody can test bytes.
This was defined by IBM in the 1960s.
Both the terminology bit and byte word is really dependent on the architecture.
OK address space.
You've seen this before.
This is.
This is a total number of uniquely identifiable locations in memory.
This is from the programmer's perspective.
So in the instructions that architecture, you have something that says address space.
From the programmers perspective, this is the memory, the size of memory.
Let's say that this processor, this this architecture has for example, in LC3, the address space is
2 to the 1616 bit addresses, which is really small.
That's why it's called a little computer.
LC stands for little computer.
OK, in MIPS, the address space is 2 to the 32.
It has 32 bit addresses, which is small, but we can extend it in the future in X8664, which is one
of the dominant micro architectures today, it's the address space is up to two to the 48.
So I have 48 that addresses.
So essentially you have two to the 48 uniquely identifiable locations in memory.
You may think that this is a lot, but we actually generating so much data that this is not a lot.
2 to the 64 is a lot more, but we're also getting there.
OK, So addressability, you've also seen this one.
We talked about memory in sequential logic lectures.
This tells you how many bits are stored in each location, and ISA also specifies this.
Basically in each address, how many bits are there from the programmer's perspective.
So keep this in mind.
We're talking about the programmer's perspective over here.
Later we're going to talk about how the hardware is designed and that could be different from the
programmer's perspective as long as the hardware obeys the programmer's perspective in the end, OK,
OK, You will understand this a lot more later on.
So for example, 8 bit addressable or byte addressable means that a byte is stored in each location
or word addressable, a word is stored in each addressable location, OK.
So whenever you give an address, it's assumed that you have a 32 bit word.
For example, if your word is 32 bits, most computers today are byte addressable.
Essentially each address, an address specifies a single byte.
OK, because people have figured out that that's a not bad granularity.
There are a lot of operations that are done on bytes.
If you make the granularity words, then the granularity is too large.
If you make the granularity bit, a lot of programs don't operate just on a single bit or a few bits.
They usually operate on 8 bits at a time.
But this may also over change over usage of computing, right?
OK, so a given instruction can operate on a byte or a word, and this is specified in the instruction
itself.
So let's give a simple example.
This is from your book also.
This is a representation of memory with eight locations.
This is going to be kind of obvious to everyone over here, but you have 8 addresses.
As you can see, each location contains 8 bits in this particular case.
So it's byte addressable memory with an address space of eight, right?
And you can figure out that value 6 is stored in address 4 and value 4 is stored in address 6.
Kind of fun.
OK, so how can we make the same size memory bit addressable?
I'm not going to draw this, but instead of having eight locations, so you have 8 locations, each is
8 bits.
So there's 64 bits over here.
So you want a 64 bit memory still.
But if you want to have a bitter, that's well, you have 64 locations and each each location contains
one bit.
OK, so your address is now 6 bits, right?
And each address specifies one bit.
OK, so this is just to warming up.
So word addressable memory.
in Word addressable memory, each data word has a unique address.
MIPS specifies a data word to be 32 bits because it happens, it so happens that in a lot of
programming languages an integer is 32 bits, right?
It was not always the case, but in modern language it's more 32 bits.
In LC3, because it's little computer a unique, you have a unique address for each 16 bit data word
if it's word addressable.
So this is what the memory looks like in a word addressable MIPS.
So basically the first word is stored this way, the second word is stored this way, The third word,
well, 0 TH word one first word, second word, third word, right?
That's address.
This is address 0, address 1, address 2, address 3.
Whenever you specify load, we're going to talk about loads.
Get data from address 0.
You will get this entire word, OK, because this is word addressable.
You cannot get a single byte, OK, OK, so this is the word address that you have.
I kind of said this already.
OK, let's talk about byte addressable memory, which is really what essentially almost all computers
are.
For example, MIPS started to be word addressable and.
They quickly realised that this was a bad idea because they figured out a lot of programs operate on
bytes, and if they don't provide an instruction that operates on bytes, they're going to lose a lot
of performance.
We're going to talk about that.
Also data types, for example, and they move to byte addressable immediately, and they haven't
changed since then.
OK, so each byte here has a unique address.
MIPS is actually byte addressable.
What I showed on this slide is actually not correct.
There's no wordeducable MIPS anymore.
MIPS is actually byte addressable.
LC3B, which is an updated version of LC3, is also byte addressable.
It's an educational ISA.
So this is what things look like, if you think about it.
So you have these words word zero, word one, word two, word 3, but you have a byte address of the
word right now.
So each word word is 32 bits in MIPS.
Yeah, a byte is 8 bits.
So I have 4 words, 4 bytes in a word, and the first byte has address 0, the second byte address,
address one.
The third byte has address as well.
Yeah, address 0, address 1, address 2, address 3, Right.
And then the second word starts with address 4, and then the third word starts at address 8, and
then the next one starts at address C That's exadecimal.
OK, that's 12 in exadecimal.
OK, this looks interesting right?
Now, the reason I showed this picture like this is because there are cases where you actually
operate on words.
Also, you don't always operate on bytes.
You sometimes operate on words.
Then the question becomes how are these 4 bytes ordered, right?
This may confuse you, but you'll get used to it.
Basically, which of the four bytes is the most significant versus least significant?
And in the end, this is going to be a convention, right?
In other words, which of assume that the data that you want to store, the least significant bytes
are ENF and the most significant bytes are 8 and 9.
Assuming you have a word that you're storing where, which address should the least significant bytes
score?
Which address should the most significant bytes score?
OK, so let's go to the next picture over here.
How many people have read Gulliver's Travels?
OK, you read it actually.
OK, so maybe how many people heard of Gulliver's Travels?
Hopefully a super set how many people never heard of this OK, now you can learn you have a reading
assignment not for this course.
It's good to do it, especially when you're a kid, but people are always kids in the end in this
there are a lot of stories Gulliver travel basically there's travels around the world and then you
you you get to some people that do things in different ways.
The whole world is like that right.
Like when I go to Australia, I have to adjust to the fact that people are driving on the left.
I'm used to countries where people drive on the right.
That's a convention, right?
It affects a lot of things within that country, but outside that country, it doesn't matter.
You just only need to obey the convention.
Now, if you travel enough to those countries where the convention is different, you get to start
behaving that way so that when you get back to a country where people drive on the right, you start
looking to the right and then you may get hit.
OK, so basically it's a convention over here.
Which side do people break their eggs here?
Do you, for example, do you break your eggs on the big side over here or the little side?
How many people do it on the big side?
Maybe people don't eat eggs, that's fine.
How many people do it on the little side?
OK, so little side wins it seems like.
So basically in in Gulliver's Travels there are people who break their eggs on the big side in
Lilliput land and then king orders them to break their eggs from the left side and then do the
people win or do the king, does the king win?
There's a good question over here and you can read the rest.
OK, so we have a similar issue over here.
Basically we have a convention issue.
We want to store a word in byte addressable memory and a word is 4 bytes.
Assume that which byte goes to lower address, OK, in big Indian world, in big Indian convention, the
least significant bit least significant byte goes to the higher address, OK.
In the little Indian world world, little Indian convention, least significant byte goes to the lower
address, OK.
So yeah, big Indian, little Indian X86 is little Indian, MIPS is little Indian, Spark was big Indian
etcetera.
So there are different Isas that choose different things.
I kind of like the Little Indian myself, but I'm biased, maybe because I like the little number to
be least significant and larger number to be more significant.
That's how I think of Little Indian, for example.
OK, is this a big deal in general?
No.
It's a convention.
The problem happens.
When you cross conventions, right, Except when one big endian system needs to communicate with a
little endian system, they need to convert the data, right?
You need to know, of course, how to lay out your data, like where do where to write the most
significant byte, for example.
If you're changing this byte over here, you need to know where exactly to write it, right?
Because you have an operation that could put a word in memory.
You have an operation that could also put only one single byte in memory, right?
You should make sure you're always consistent.
OK, so basically this is not a big deal, but it's something you need to know.
So for example, when you go to Singapore or Hong Kong or Australia or UK, then obey the convention
over there, switch your mind so that you don't get killed on the road for some reason.
Now you can guess what the reason is because people are driving on the left as opposed to right
threat.
And if you drive on the left, right as opposed to left over there, you may have even more trouble.
OK, OK, so that's big Indian versus little Indian.
You will need to think about that.
OK, let's talk about accessing memory.
So we're talking about memory still in the one Neumann model.
There are two ways of accessing memory in the one Neumann model.
You need to read or load data from a memory location to somewhere.
We're going to talk about what that somewhere is later on.
Usually registers that are in the processor or you write or store data to a memory location.
OK, so 2 registers are usually used to access memory, memory address register and memory data
register.
These are in the original von Neumann model, but you don't have to have these very, very explicitly
in existing systems in an ISA.
So these are not part of the ISA necessarily.
But in implementation, you need to have some things like this.
Whenever you implement memory address register, as the name implies, you have an address in a thread
to be able to read.
There are multiple steps.
Basically everything is algorithmic.
You have a step where you load the MAR memory address register with the address you wish to read
from.
In the second step, data in the corresponding location gets placed in the MDR by the memory.
You know exactly how the memory places the data, right?
You remember that little memory structure that we built?
You supply the address, it goes to memory address register.
Think about memory address register like a register.
It gets latched there and then you wait for one cycle.
At the end of the cycle, the data in that address gets latched into the memory data register.
It doesn't need to be one single clock cycle as we will see later on.
This could be multiple clock cycles also.
You just need to know how long it takes so that you can design your finite state machine to ensure
that you read the data from the memory data register after the memory response.
So hopefully things are becoming a bit clear.
Right now you have a memory address register, you have memory array and then you have a memory data
register and memory array can take some time.
And you basically adjust to that time when you build your system, we're going to get back to that
again to write you basically in the first step, you load the MAR with the address.
Basically you put the, you write the address that you're going to get the data from into the MAR and
also, oh, sorry, the address you're going to write to into the MAR and you write into MDR the data
that you wish to write to that location.
OK, So you write to both MAR and MDR and you also activate a write enable signal in Step 2.
At this point, the value in MDR gets written to the address specified by MAR after some amount of
time, OK.
And that amount of time needs to be specified, But we're not going to talk about timing at this
moment.
We're going to talk about that later on.
And memory timing is going to be one of the worst things that you'll ever deal with if you ever deal
with computing system design because that's the big bottleneck that we have today.
OK, but let's not talk about signing.
But these are actually 2 very simple things that we do to read and write data from memory.
And we're done with memory for now.
We're going to get back to it a lot.
But this is the models assumptions about what should memory do.
Let's talk about the processing unit.
So this processing unit is actually the unit that performs the actual computation.
It can consist of many functional units, many Alus.
You can think of it that way.
We start with a simple arithmetic logic unit that you have seen.
It executes computational logic operations, but the ISA specifies what should the ALU do.
So in LC3 there are only very basic operations, add and not.
But you know that that's enough.
In fact only NAND is enough right they all.
But this having more operations simplifies the programmers or compilers job, right?
XOR is also added in LC3B for example.
In MIPS there are a lot more add, subtract, multiply and NOR shift left logical shift right logical
set less than...
In fact, original MIPS didn't multiply because we will see the philosophy.
To MIPS.
Later when we talk about design philosophies of execution models, their philosophy was we will keep
the hardware as simple as possible, but the compiler will be complex to exploit the underlying
simple hardware.
So we can design it fast, but the performance will come from the software and they figured out this
was not a good idea.
Well, not the philosophy itself.
Philosophy has some benefits, but it's limited.
Also, as we will see later, they removed a lot of the instructions like byte adjustability.
They added back in the next iteration very quickly.
Multiply, they said people can do multiply.
Why do we need a multiply?
Compiler can do adds and shifts.
They quickly understood that that was a bad idea because nobody wants to do adds and shifts with a
compiler.
They basically want I want a multiply instruction, right?
Today we want even more than a multiply.
I want a matrix multiply instruction, right?
People have added matrix multiply instructions in MIPS.
It doesn't exist, but those instructions exist actually in Exceed 6 and other architectures, for
example.
OK, so basically this is the hardware software interface and you could add more to it of course.
So the ALU processes quantities that are referred to as words.
That's what word is actually word length and LC3 is 16 bits.
What the ALU processes word length and MIPS is 32 bits.
That's the maximum word length.
ALU can also process a byte, for example, but there needs to be an instruct specification in the
instruction that says that process byte or process word.
OK, we will see that also.
So recall we built the say Lu, at least one version of the say Lu.
It doesn't satisfy the requirements of MIPS nor LC3.
Actually, it may satisfy LC3, but I don't look at it.
It may be too powerful for LC3.
It satisfies the requirements of a subset of MIPS.
And you remember this picture awfully.
There's another thing in the processing unit which is stored.
It's called the processing unit, but we're going to add storage to it because memory is so
important.
This is called fast temporary storage.
Basically, it's almost always the case that remove that.
Almost it's always the case that a computer provides a small amount of storage very close to ALU.
And the reason is the memory as we defined it is too slow if you want it to be big.
OK, we'll see that also.
Again, the purpose of this small memory or small amount of storage is to store temporary values and
quickly access them later.
So for example, if you want to do this calculation A + B * C / D, you have a bunch of intermediate
values, right?
For example, the intermediate result of A+B, you, you, let's say you bring A from a location memory.
You bring B from a location memory, do the calculation the ALU, there's an intermediate result
that's called Y You want to multiply it by C What do you do?
You take Y, store it to memory, and then you go to memory and say I want Y again, bring it back, and
then bring C and then multiply Y&C, right?
People have figured out that this is a bad idea because you're going to memory unnecessarily to
store Y and read Y again.
Why not actually put something close to the processing unit where you store these intermediate
values?
Basically, the reason is it's too slow to store each ALU result in memory and then retrieve it again
for future use, right?
So whenever you have these temporary values or intermediate values, or whenever you have a value
that's used more than once, you have this issue, right?
For example, if you want to do many, many things on a, it doesn't make sense to go to memory and get
a every time you need a, right?
Why not just store it close to the ALU?
And this is the, the main reason is MMA access much slower than addition, multiplication, or
division.
And that disparity is increasing.
Today we'll talk about that more.
That's true for all intermediate results and all multiple users of different variables.
So this temporary storage is called registers.
It's implemented as registers that we've seen, but it's not necessarily implemented exact that way.
But it's called registers at the architecture level.
And the the so one of these, one of the one location is called the register.
And the unity of all the locations that can store these temporary results is called the register
file.
It's essentially a small amount of memory, a small memory array that can store some number of
values, and the number of values is defined in the ISA.
Again, instruction set architecture.
I'll give you some examples.
So basically you have fast temporary storage.
We've kind of said this memory is large but slow, we don't want to access it.
Registers in the processing unit to ensure fast access to values to be processed in the ALU.
Typically one register contains one word, same as word length.
And the register set or also called register file is the set of registers that can be manipulated by
instructions.
This is very important.
They are visible to the programmer.
We will see a whole lot of other registers that are not visible to the programmer that cannot be
manipulated by the programmer.
These are going to be manipulated by software and programmer.
So for example LC3 Little computer 3.
Being a little computer, it has eight general purpose registers, only 8.
It has also some special purpose registers that we're going to see soon when we talk about control.
But these are general purpose, meaning you can do put anything in them.
OK?
X86, which is the most common architecture, initially had only 8 registers.
People extended over time to have much more because people needed more of these registers because
they don't want to go to memory, right?
So R0 through R7 is a three bit register number.
If you have 8 general purpose registers, you can address them with three bits.
So this is essentially fast memory.
You can think of it that way, fast memory that are specially accessible by instructions directly.
You don't need to have a memory address as we will see.
Generate the memory address, the memory address, the address of the registers are going to be
encoded in the instruction itself, as we will see.
OK register size in LC3 is 16 bits, which is the word length of LC3.
MIP says 32 general purpose registers, 5 bit register number or register ID.
And you can, you can put any value you want in them.
And ideally you would like to put the values that you're using right now over and over and over and
over.
For example, if you're multiplying a with 200 different things, you'd better have a inside a
register.
You bring from memory, put it into the register, and then do the calculations or 200 calculations.
Register size in MIPS is 32 bits.
OK, this is how a register can be built.
Remember we called this register.
Unfortunately, there is a terminology issue here.
The register at the logic level is implemented this way.
Essentially, it's a a number of flip flops in parallel, right?
There's a four bit register.
This is AD flip flop based register.
A register can be implemented using SRAM also, as we will see, essentially whatever is fast would be
good over here.
You don't want to implement a register using DRAM cells.
We're going to talk about that later on.
This is what's visible to the programmer.
I'm going to later show you some ISA manuals where ISA specifies, for example, what's usually
conventionally goes to different registers.
But you can ignore all these and do your own programming.
OK, so you can see that, for example, there's actually one interesting thing that you cannot ignore,
which is register zero.
You cannot write to register 0 because register #0 means that there is a value 0 there.
So if you whenever you want to actually do something with a 0, just use register zero.
Don't load anything with a 0, just use register zero.
That's hard wired to zero, OK?
Everything else you can do different things with.
We're going to see that in more assembly programming.
OK, let me cover input and output because they're going to be quick and then we'll take a break.
So input and output, both of these, as you can see, they're used to enable information to get into
and out of a computer, which is really important clearly, right?
We want to communicate with the computer.
Many devices can be used for input and output.
They're called peripheral devices.
So input can be keyboard, mouse, scanner, discs, you know your brain eyes depending on what the
computer is, right?
Output, GEMI, monitor, printer, disk, etcetera.
Right, In LC3, we will consider keyboard and monitor and we're actually going to develop memory
mapped IO later on in LC3.
But the scenario that we're not going to go into a whole lot of more detail, memory mapped IO, as we
will see very briefly later on, is you can actually map these inputs and outputs to memory
locations.
There are some special system level functions that enable you to do that in ISA, in structured
architecture.
And you can use instructions that you access memory with to also access input and output devices.
OK, I'll leave it at that for now.
OK, so let's take a break.
We're going to talk about the control unit.
It'll take some time to talk about the control unit because that's going to orchestrate all of
these.
And then we're going to hopefully get into ISA.
So let's be back.
OK, what am I looking at by 1517?
The sound is good right online.
OK, OK, now we covered 4 components of the one Neumann model, memory processing unit, inputs,
output.
Now we're going to cover perhaps one of the hallmarks of the one Neumann model, the control unit,
because how you control these components makes a huge difference.
So a control unit is it's like the conductor of an orchestra.
How many people have seen an orchestra play a Symphony, for example?
You've probably seen it, right?
And there are all kinds of things that are going on.
And then the conductor really makes sense of all of those things, right?
It really orchestrates what should happen first, second, next, in parallel, etcetera.
Essentially, it conducts a step by step process of executing a program.
Or in more detail, it conducts a step by step process of executing every instruction in a program in
sequence in the von Neumann model, right?
So to be able to do that, it keeps track of which instruction is being processed via something
called an instruction register, which contains the instruction itself.
This is really the bits of the instruction.
So if you have 32 bits in an instruction, you have 32 bits storage over here.
If you have 16 bits like we will see in LC3, you have 16 bits.
And we'll see instructions today a lot and tomorrow.
And also needs to keep track of the next instruction to process or sometimes the current
instruction, depending on when you change this thing via program counter PC or instruction pointer
IP.
These are the same thing.
Another register that contains the address of the instruction to process at some point this points
to the next instruction, right?
So you have a program counter that's points to the instruction that you're going to process next.
And then you have the instruction register which has the bits of the instruction that you're going
to process right now.
OK, program counter is really because it's a sequential execution model.
You increment the program counter, you always go to the next address, right, Unless you're going to
change the flow of control.
As we will see later on, Intel calls this instruction pointer, which is probably a much better term
than program counter.
It basically points to the instruction you're going to process next.
So a nice terminology, but it didn't really stick apart from the Intel world.
OK, so we've kind of defined what's called the programmer visible state right now.
So this consists of memory.
This is an array of storage locations indexed by an address.
We've already discussed this.
This consists of registers, general purpose registers.
These are given special names in the ISA as opposed to memory addresses.
These are their own addresses, but they're encoded in the instruction itself.
As we will see, there are also some special purpose registers that we're going to ignore for now.
Perhaps the most important special purpose register is really a program counter.
It's really the memory address of the current or next instruction depending on when it changes.
OK, now you will see when it changes, when you actually implement your processors.
So these are registers and memory that are visible to the programmer.
That's also called programmer visible or architectural state.
This is going to become very important when we talk about other things like speculation down the
line.
So instructions and programs specify how to transform the values of programmer visible state.
That's also important.
Basically, we're going to define instructions to operate on these, OK?
And these are going to be the inputs to the instructions partially and the outputs that will be
modified by the instructions, OK?
So now you can think of an instruction processing engine, right?
You have these inputs that are actually registers and memory that are stateful elements and you have
outputs also these stateful elements.
So you're processing logic can be some combinational logic that takes the inputs and that produces
the outputs.
So this is your state.
Your state is completely specified by this.
You have program counter that is the address of the instruction that you're supposed to execute.
And in a cycle you execute that instruction and you produce the next state.
So you can express essentially an ISA as specifying A finite state machine, right, as we will see.
So what we're going to cover in this lecture and the next lecture is basically specify how
instructions transform this state.
The next state, OK, and once you have that information, you have the instruction set.
Every instruction specifies how state which is this can be transformed.
The next state which is also this, but modified in some way.
Now you can build a finite state machine that executes all of the instructions, right?
Hopefully this is clear.
OK, And we're going to do that.
Actually, we're going to build a finite state machine that takes the state and transforms it based
on the specification of an instructor architecture that we're going to develop to the next state
for every possible instruction that's described in this hardware software interface.
Sounds good.
OK, So we've covered the von Neumann model.
This is a model of execution.
That's the dominant model.
There are two key properties.
These are the most important properties of the von Neumann model.
Actually, that is shaped how computers have developed.
One is stored program, the other is sequential instruction processing.
Stored program is actually very simple.
Both of them are simple.
Actually.
Instructions are stored in a linear memory array.
Memory is unified between instructions and data.
And the interpretation of a stored value, whether it's instructions or data, depends on the control
signals.
We'll discuss control signals later.
Depends on whether the program counter points to that value.
OK.
If you think about it, whether you have an AD, if you have an address inside the PC, you go to that
address, you interpret that 32 bit value or whatever bit value, it's specified by the ISA as an
instruction.
OK, We'll see more of this when we actually build this engine.
The second property is sequential instruction processing.
Basically, I already said this, but one instruction is processed.
We're going to talk about instruction processing cycle today.
Process means fetched, executed, completed.
There are a couple more things over there at a time.
And the program counter or instruction pointer identifies the current instruction that you're
processing and at some point it gets incremented to point to the next instruction.
And program counters advance sequentially except for control transfer instructions, branches as we
will call them, or jumps.
OK.
But the key is you process 1 instruction at a time, you finish that instruction, and then you
actually process the next instruction, finish that instruction, and then you process the next
instruction, OK?
So you keep transforming the state to next state, 1 instruction at a time.
You don't do multiple instructions, you don't do instructions in some odd order.
It's all sequential order, right?
OK, so basically it's stored program and sequential instruction processing.
Always remember this.
OK, now let's build not built, but let's talk about a Von Neumann machine and what its hardware
software interface would look like.
We're not going to build it right now, but I'm going to give you some examples of how some of the
instructions can be buildable with things that we have partially seen.
But essentially everything is a von Neumann machine today, although they have non von Neumann
elements to it as we will see in later lectures.
But at least the general purpose components that we have over here are von Neumann machines.
For example, these cores, performance cores, efficiency cores, they use the RMISA with some
extensions, this Intel, these performance cores and efficiency cores, they also use, they use the
X86 ISA.
This also used the X8664 ISA and this use the IBM Power ISA.
So we're going to talk about ISAISAS, instructions and architecture.
These all differ in terms of how they specify different things, as we will see.
So we're going to look at something like this.
Let me introduce some of these because we're going to put instructions on top of this.
But if you look over here, there is the memory, there's the MAR memory address register, memory data
register, there's the input and output keyboards and display.
There is the processing unit with some components.
You see, you can see the register file over here, right?
There are two source register inputs, 2 addresses that you can read.
You can read 2 registers, and you can write to one register destination register.
So you can build this today.
Actually, it's kind of a memory structure with the flip flops.
And then there's an ALU over here, as you can see, arithmetic logic unit which can do four different
types of operations, ALU control.
And then there is a bus over here.
And remember these things, the tri-state buffers, yeah, you can put the result of the ALU on the
tri-state buffer using the tri-state buffer here onto this wire set of wires bus.
And then memory can capture it, for example, either in the address register or the data register.
And you can put something else over here, the program counter, for example, if you want to fetch the
instruction.
OK, and there's a big control unit over here.
Not everything exactly is the control unit.
Actually this is all the control unit you can increment.
At the program counter, for example, there's some logic that you can add.
You have a finite state machine that controls decoding the instruction, what instruction you're
processing.
OK, let me introduce some of these signals.
We're not, we're going to look at this more, but there's some control signals that control
multiplexers.
For example, AL us, whether you load a register, whether you enable memory, whether you read or
write to memory, whether you actually whether you load the register file, There's some data signals
there.
They're usually distinguished with these black arrows as opposed to empty white arrows over here,
which are control signals.
There is this memory which is 16 bit addressable.
In LC3, there's a memory address register.
I kind of said all of this without animating, but now let's animate.
There's a keyboard, there's a monitor.
There's the Lu which has 2 inputs, 1 output.
There's a register file which has eight general purpose registers, instruction register.
Remember, in the control unit, there's a program counter which is also part of the control unit, and
the program counter is incremented over here.
These other parts come from changing the program counter using a jump, as we will see.
And there's a finite state machine for generating control signals to ensure that what is specified
by the instruction is done right.
That's one of the purposes.
There's a clock that's really important for finite state machines.
As you can see, that determines the frequency at which things the state is updated.
There's an ALU operation control signal, There's a gate ALU control signal, the tri-state buffer
that basically enables the gating of the output of the ALU onto the bus.
There's a gate.
PCI could keep doing this, but you can see that somebody constructed this.
We didn't constructed this, We didn't construct this, right?
Somebody construct this, threw it at us.
Of course, I kind of know how it operates, so I'm going to give you the high level of how things get
executed on this.
OK, so basically we're going to execute a program on this, but we're going to start with
instructions first.
Essentially, instructions and data are stored in memory.
Typically the instruction length is the word length and the processor fetches instruction from
memory sequentially.
It fetches 1 instruction, it decodes the instruction, figures out what it is.
Remember the decoder instructions are encoded in some way.
You have some bits saying this instruction does something that is specified in a manual.
If bit is 0000, the instruction should be add, for example, right?
And somebody needs to decode this and we're going to use a decoder for that.
And then the processor executes the instruction and then continues with the next instruction, right?
The address of the current instructions stored in the program counter.
If you have word addressable memory, the processor increments the program counter by one.
In LC3, if you have byte addressable memory, the processor increments the program counter by the
instruction length in bytes, which is 4 bytes.
So you increment PC gets PC Plus 4 after the processing of every instruction.
OK, so there's also some more details.
The operating system typically sets PC to something.
This is going to change when we talk about virtual memory in Lecture 2526, for example.
But basically you start from some point.
OK, so let's take a look at a sample program stored in memory.
No need to understand the program.
Now you have 4 instructions over here.
This is assembly code.
You're you're going to get familiar with it in your labs.
These are 4 instructions that are stored in memory.
And if you had the ISA manual of MIPS, you could translate all of these instructions to this machine
code.
Essentially each of them is 32 bits.
And based on what you've seen over here and based on your understanding of what's the source
register, what's the destination register, you could generate this machine code.
This is the machine code or bit level representation of this a little bit more human readable code,
right?
OK.
And that's what gets stored in memory locations, right?
This is the first instruction.
As I said, OS sets the program to start at this address and the first instruction gets stored over
here, and the operating system sets the program counter to be there when it loads the program.
So there's some other things that happens so that you can start executing a program, which we're not
covering right now.
But if it's the operating system you start from, you start from some point to begin with, right?
OK, So basically the program counter points to the first instruction that gets executed, and the
program counter moves to the next instruction that gets executed.
So you keep doing this, right?
So the question becomes, how do you execute an instruction, right?
An instruction is the most basic unit of computer processing.
Instructions are the language of a computer, if you think about it right, language of the ISA,
language of a particular computer architecture, and ISA is the vocabulary of it.
This can be written as machine language as I showed you, that's computer readable.
Assembly language, which is human readable arguably, as long as you have some.
I guess you could read the machine language also, but you have to have very special skills to decode
it very quickly, right?
It's possible also human readable, but very few human humans are capable of that.
More humans are capable of the machine language reading.
Even more humans are capable of a higher level representation right?
So we will study LC3 instructions and MIPS instructions.
But principles are really similar in all of the ISAS.
X86 for example is a very complicated ISA.
It has principles that are similar and quoting principles, etcetera.
It has a lot more complexity though.
OK, So what is an instruction made-up of?
Essentially there are two parts to an instruction.
1 is opcode, the other is operens.
Opcode specifies what the instruction does.
An operand specify who the instruction is to do that thing to, right?
What does it operate on?
Basically both are specified in the instruction format itself, or it's called instruction encoding.
So for example, an LC3 instruction consists of 16 bits.
You can represent as bits.
15 through 00 is the least significant little NDN.
OK, and this is what we have over here.
This is 1 specification, right?
The top 4 bits is the OP code.
The remaining parts specify the operands OK Bits 15 through 12 specify the up code, and there's
sixteen distinct up codes.
0001 happens to be add OK.
Why is it add and why is not multiply?
Because the designer decided.
The designer who designed the instruction set decided that way.
Go ask them.
Don't ask me, OK, Basically it's there's a lot of design that goes into it also.
That's what I mean, you know, they don't there.
There are also some ISA trade-offs that we will briefly cover later on.
But in the end it's written in this book.
There is no magic in determining what is the, what is the up code of an ad unless you memorise the
up codes, right?
You could you could go and read the 4000 page X86 manual and tell me the up code of every
instruction.
It wouldn't be a nice exercise, but you could do it.
Or if someone asks you the up code of ADD, you go and look at the manual and say this is the up
code, right?
It's just, it's what is specified in the manual and the remaining bits are used to figure out where
the up hands are.
Bits 11 through 0 and there will be different ways of figuring out up ands.
In this particular case, this happens to be an operate instruction, and because of the value of bit
5, this is interpreted as a register number R6, and this interprets R2, this interprets R6.
So this is adding R2 to R6 and writing the result into R6 because of the way of the specification,
as we will see soon.
OK, But there are three main types of instructions.
You've seen operate types, operate instructions, execute operations in the ALU.
OK, we're going to see that those first.
And then there are data movement instructions that read from or write to memory.
And then there are control flow instructions that change the sequence of execution.
These are three main types.
If you come up with a new type, let me know.
Let's start with some example instructions.
So addition, I've shown you, this is what you want to achieve at the high level code, right?
A = B + C Let's assume that that's the highest level abstraction we have for addition in assembly
level.
You can write it like this.
Add ABC.
This assumes that the first variable is the output, right?
This is destination basically.
So add the mnemonic to indicate the operation to perform.
B&C are called source operands and A is the destination operand at the assembly level right?
So this is the semantics of operation of this instruction.
At the assembly level, A gets B + C right?
So in ISA we map variables to registers essentially.
So for example, in LC3 you may decide to map BCA like this.
They respectively go to R1R 2R0.
There are 8 registers.
Remember in MIPS you may decide to map things like this.
This is the MIPS convention.
OK, again, why is the convention like this?
As someone else I didn't develop it.
I like R much better.
It says register right?
OK so this is how you would write the same thing in LC3 assembly add R0R 1R2.
So remember R2R0 is destination.
So the the implicit convention is that the destination comes first.
OK, so the field values look like this.
Again you look up the manual and say add is an up code of 1 and then if you want to do R0 this is
destination register.
You set a value of 0 over here because this is R0.
This is source register one.
You set a value of 1001.
These are three bit values.
And then the format says the second source register should be specified over here.
The bottom 3 bits you set to 010, which is 2, and then this bit definitely has to be 0, and these
two bits also have to be 0.
Why?
Because the manual says so.
OK And the machine code is basically translating this to a 16 bit value and these are the bits and
this is in hexadecimal writing.
OK, that's how you get to the machine code.
Basically, there's an encoding for the up code and there's an encoding for the operands that are
specified by the format of the instruction that's dictated by this manual called Instructions and
Architecture Manual.
OK, so you essentially have a format or encoding of instructions and it happens to be like this in
LC3 for operate.
For all operate instructions that are operating on registers, the the top 4 bits are the up codes,
the next three bits specify destination register, the next three bits specify the first source
register, and the next three bits are 0, and the last three bits specify source register two.
OK, somebody encoded the operate instructions this way.
The designer, I think I already said this up code specifies what the instruction does add is 0001
and happens to be 01/01 for example.
And how do you distinguish between them?
You read those 4 bits supplied into a four to 16 decoder that raises only one line and one line
belongs to AT the other line belongs to AT.
OK, you know what that decoder looks like 4 to 16 decoder.
We have designed decoders OK and SR1 and SR2 are source register that are going to supply to the
register file as addresses.
So a register file remember has two ports SR1 and SR2.
These will be routed through wires from the instruction register to the inputs address inputs or the
register file.
Dr.
is going to be the destination register, and that's going to be routed as the destination register
address to the register file.
OK, so you can actually implement all of these things, right?
We've actually done this.
You can implement an adder also, we talk about bit serial address, for example.
OK, so semantics is the data value in SR1 gets added to data value in SR2 and that data value gets
stored into destination register address.
And and is very similar, except it's not an addition operation, it's an AND logical AND operation.
And this is what the book shows, for example, right?
This is what I showed you earlier also.
OK, OK, let's take a look at the same thing in MIPS.
It's going to be very similar basically, except MIPS instructions happen to be 32 bits so you have
more values.
This may look ridiculous right now, but that's how it is.
The up code is 0, but this basically specifies Rs plus RT should be stored in Rd.
So the value in Rs should be added to the value in RT and that should be stored in destination
register.
So this is how things get mapped in MIPS.
This is the encoding.
So it happens that by convention, S 0 is register 17 in MIPS, and then I don't remember which one's
which.
See, even I get confused.
So this is register 17, I guess.
OK, let's do it the nice way.
I'm not going to do that.
See, you don't need to memorize anything because this is kind of a waste of let's say brain cells.
Maybe you just look up things and I'm not so intelligent to remember the entire myths manual which
is 1000 plus pages probably.
OK, but basically the our type instruction format says there are three register op eds op code is 0.
This is our type instruction format.
It's not just add Rs and RT are source registers.
See, I made a mistake earlier.
So RSRT, yeah.
Anyway, RSNRT are source registers.
Each of them is five bits, because you have 32 registers and you have 32 bits.
In the instruction encoding Rd.
specifies the destination register.
Shift amount is only for shift operations.
Ignore that for now.
Again, descent encoding funct is the most important thing actually here in addition to the 0, this
is really a part of the up code actually.
So MIPS decided that if this value is 0, this also is part of the up code.
So if this value is 0, this function specifies what operate operations you have.
So in this particular case, for example, if this value is 0 and if this is 32, that specifies an AD.
We're going to see more of that.
So we're going to get to that.
So that's the format of our type in MIPS.
We're going to see more.
Let's talk about memory operations.
With operate instructions such as addition, we tell the computer to execute.
Refute things, right?
But we need instructions to access the operands from memory if they are in memory, if they're not in
registers, for example.
Because at some point you need to load the registers from things in memory.
If there are already registers, that's good, you can use what we had.
But now how do you load things into the registers?
You have to have instructions that load the operands from memory to registers.
That's the function of load, store operations.
Load and store.
Essentially, store them from registers to memory.
So we're going to see how to read from memory, and then we're going to see how to write.
But first let's see the load operation.
Store operation is the opposite.
We will talk about that a little bit later.
So this is the load word.
So this is what we would like to do.
This is one example of loading a variable from an array, right?
The base address of the array is a or the name of the array is a.
And you want to get the data at index.
I right?
This is the assembly code you load into array from base address A and index I some value into a
variable a.
OK, so this is a mnemonic to indicate load word operation.
This is the base address of the array.
This is the offset array of the array.
This also called immediate or literal.
It's a constant essentially and a is the destination operate.
So semantics says at the assembly level little a variable gets the value in memory location whose
addresses A plus I.
OK, OK, let's do load word.
This is word reducible.
That's why it's a plus I with byte addressable that a plus I will change.
Let's do load word in LC3 and MIPS LC three assembly looks like this where now let's put two over
here.
If you actually have a variable like this two, you can encode in the instruction.
OK, so LDR load register, the destination register is R3R0 contains the base address A and #2 is
basically the index value.
OK, so the semantics is R3 destination register gets the value in memory from the location whose
address is computed with base register R0 added to it.
Index that's inside the instruction 2.
Hopefully that's clear.
All of these are encoded in the instruction and the semantics is depend on the specification of the
instruction.
This manual ISA manual MIPS assembly is going to be very similar.
Essentially we're going to translate the same thing.
We're going to assume word reducible, MIPS is not word reducible.
LC3 is word reducible.
But if MIPS were word reducible, it looks like this.
You can see it's kind of similar, right?
So basically S3 register gets the value stored in memory location whose address is computed by
adding the value in S0 with this immediate value 2 that is specified in the instruction.
OK, so this is we're going to call talk about addressing modes in the next lecture.
But these particular instructions use an addressing mode called base plus offset.
You have a base register, you're adding an immediate offset value to it.
There's a very commonly used addressing mode that you have to access memory.
And the reason one one of the reasons developed is because of arrays array indexing.
As you can see, right, Array has a base address and then array has an index you want to index into.
OK, let's take a look at load word and byte addressable MIPS.
Essentially MIPS assembly in this case, translate to not 2, but four.
Basically here the goal is to access the second word, right?
Not the odd word, not the first word, the second word.
And if you want to get to the bytes, the first byte of the second word in a byte addressable machine
where each word is 4 bytes, you multiply 2 by 4, right?
That's the idea over here.
And the semantics is very similar.
So byte address is calculated as word address times bytes divided by bird and bytes divided word is
4 in MIPS.
If LC3 were byte addiscible, then you have two bytes for word because a word is 16 bits in LC3.
Again, this is defined by the ISA.
Somebody defined it.
OK, so this is called an instruction format with immediate.
This is different from the operate format actually, and you can see that this is actually a load
instruction.
And this is what we've seen, right?
The format in LC3 looks like this.
The up code for LDR is 6 and OP code is always at the top 4 bits.
In LC3, destination register is always in the next 3 bits, bits 11 through 8.
In this case it's three Bayes register.
The format specifies that Bayes register is the next 3 bits, bits 8 through 6.
And the format specifies that you have a six bit offset right two.
Now, you can immediately say that you're limited to the number of bits in the offset when you're
doing this sort of addressing, and you're absolutely right, you can specify.
Offset that's limited by the number of bits over there.
OK, we're going to get to that.
MIPS is very similar.
As you can see, the top five bits is the up code.
In this case, you don't have an extended up code somewhere else.
This is the up code of an upload word.
It happens to be 35.
The source register is 16, the destination register is 19, and the immediate value is.
The is.
The next is the last 16 bits.
So the immediate value, the offset is much larger in MIPS because the instruction encoding is 32
bits as opposed to 16 bits, right?
So you can encode a much larger index to index an array, for example.
OK, OK, we're going to go into more instructions.
But before we do that, let's talk about the processing cycle of an instruction.
So basically, you hopefully have seen there's a way to specify instructions and encode instructions,
and someone needs to do that and you get an ISA.
Manual describes all of that.
The question is, how do you execute these instructions, right?
That manual is useful for programming.
That manual is useful for also building the computer, right?
Let's talk about building the computer by using these instructions.
We know how to tell the computer to execute computation in the ALU, for instance, using an addition
or access operands from memory.
The question is how are these executed?
So the process of executing a single instruction is called an instruction cycle or instruction
processing cycle.
This has nothing to do with it clock cycle.
It's really the processing cycle of an instruction and each instruction essentially goes through
some steps or phases.
These are the comprehensive set of phases that we will consider.
6 phases.
Not every instruction go through all the phases.
LDR for example, load register does not require executing the ALU executors assumed to be in the
ALU, right?
It doesn't require it.
It has an evaluate address that you need to do some computation with base plus offset, remember, but
it doesn't have any additional computation.
Add does not require evaluating address because the operands are already in the registers, right?
There is no memory address that you need to evaluate for AT Intel X86 instruct.
Intel X86 happens to be one of the most complicated IS as that have ever been developed, let's say,
and there are many, many instructions over there.
One instruction actually has some instructions, can load a data value from memory, add it to a data
value in a register, and write the data value back to memory.
That requires both memory address calculation as well as execution, as you can see, and it basically
requires all of the six phases.
Let's go through these phases, essentially a program.
Each instruction goes through these these phases and then you go to the next instruction and you
keep repeating this until the program stops with an instruction.
OK, or someone powers off your computer maybe?
OK, the fetch phase obtains the instruction from memory and loads it into the instruction register.
I mean, you talked about the instruction register, right?
This phase is common to every instruction type.
Every instruction type goes through it because you actually do it.
Before you know what the instruction is, you need to fetch the bits belonging to that encoding that
is in memory, right?
So the complete description looks like this.
You load the memory address register with the contents of the program counter, which points to the
instruction that you want to get.
And you simultaneously increment the PC so that you point to the next instruction, right?
Because at some point you don't need this program counter.
And then you interrogate memory, ask the memory, get me the data from address that I stored in your
MAR and the results instruction bits get placed in MDR by memory.
You know how that is done.
We've discussed it kind of in earlier lectures.
We're going to see more of that later on.
And memory, once the memory places the data into the MDR, you take that data, the contents of MDR,
which are the bits of the instruction, essentially encoding of the instruction, and you place them
into the instruction register.
Now at the end of the fetch phase, you have the instruction register containing the bits of the
instruction belonging to location address by the program counter.
That's how you fetch the instruction.
OK, let's take a look at how this is done with the machine that we were thrown with.
Let's say this is somebody designed this, they gave it to us.
You can see that there's a program counter over here.
First step, what you do is you set the control signal such that program counter gets gated onto the
bus.
So you set the control signal such that this is one, this tri-state buffer is enabled and this
tri-state buffer is not enabled.
So that goes through over here.
And at the end of the clock cycle, data gets latched.
Well, the contents of program counter gets latched into MAR, right?
You need to set the control signals according.
We're going to talk more about that.
And concurrently program counter gets incremented by one.
At the end of the clock cycle, you have PC Plus fun.
So at the end of this clock cycle, you're pointing to the next instruction you access.
Using MAR, that takes some time and eventually memory response, hopefully in one clock cycle, let's
say.
But you could actually change that as we will see later on.
The data is in mem Dr.
Now that data is actually the bits belonging to the program counter address in memory that is
pointed to my program counter.
And the next step is really taking that and placing that into the instruction register.
OK, so the bits are over here you gate MDR.
Sorry, there's a control signal.
You'd place that data onto the wire and that wire is also connected to the IR.
At the end of the clock cycle, data gets latched into IR.
OK, So assuming that these are implemented correctly, you should be able to fetch an instruction
using these three steps.
And based on my description of this micro architecture and three clock cycles, right?
So you can see that fetch phase can take 3 clock cycles.
We will see that in the finite state machine soon.
Also OK decode identifies the instruction.
It also generates a set of control signals to process the identified instruction in later phases of
the instruction cycle.
So basically decode is very important.
That's where you understand what you're dealing with and you also generate some control signals that
are going to be useful for you later on.
And this is all done by the basic thing is really this decoder.
You have a four to 16 decoder that identifies which of the 16 up codes are going to be processed.
So the input is 4 bits from coming from the instruction register, top 4 bits of the instruction
register.
The remaining 12 bits identify what else is needed to process instruction, which is the operands as
we will see, or part of the extended opcode in MIPS.
So a decode in an LC3 implementation looks like this.
You have the instruction, the instruction register, you take the top 4 bits, supply them to some
logic that we will see that provides you what you're going to deal with at and or whatever the
control signals will be supplied.
We will see that magic later on.
For now it's magic, but you can guess what that could be, right?
It all.
It essentially generates the set of control signals to process the instruction, though these are the
control signals.
But that's a magic component for now.
But you can see that that's a finite state machine, right?
That controls actually what we're going to do with this with all of the instructions.
So recall decoder, that's a two to four.
We have a four to 16 decoder in this case.
And recall when I introduced the decoder, I said that it could be an instruction.
The program and the processor needs to decide what action to take based on instruction up code.
Basically inputs are the up code in this particular case.
OK, so this is what's to come, the full state of of state machine of LC3B.
Actually, again, I don't expect you to understand this, but this X, this is the finite state machine
of belonging to a micro architecture that implements all of the instructions in LC3B, the byte
addressable version in this case.
There's a fetch phase over here which does what I said right.
There are three clock cycles and if the memory is not ready, you stay in this clock cycle, for
example.
So you can actually have multi cycle memory and there's a decode phase and you can see that decode
phase branches out to 16 other things belonging to 16 up codes.
OK, So you go to a different state depending on the up code.
OK, OK.
You'll become more familiar with that later on.
So there's then the next, next phase is the evaluate address phase.
This computes the address of the memory location that is needed to process the instruction.
This phase necessary in LDR, it computes the address of the data word that is to be read from memory
by adding a an offset to the content of a register.
It's not necessary in AD, so you don't do this in AD.
So if you look at this LDR calculate the address by adding a register and an immediate.
So this is the specification.
You have a base register.
Some bits from the instruction register specify your base register.
So you connect them to this SR1 input, and the output of the register file gives you the contents of
the value of the base register.
You have another adder over here that's not shown in this picture, but you add to it some bits
coming from the instruction register and you place them into the MAR.
OK, that's the idea.
OK.
That's how you evaluate the address.
Fetch operands obtains the source operands needs to process the instruction in LDR.
Well, I kind of got ahead of myself.
I placed that address into MAR, but you do it in fetch operands.
You load MAR with the address calculated in the evaluate address and then you read memory.
It's very similar to the fetching an instruction, except MAR is loaded with an address that's
calculated in a different way.
You don't load the memory address register with the contents of the PC, you load the memory address
register with the contents of base register plus offset, right?
So it's going to be very similar.
In ADS, you obtain the source or operands from the register file.
Yeah, in some microprocessors you can actually fetch while decoding things, but we'll see that later
on also.
So fetch your operands.
Let's take a look at LDR.
You calculate the address.
Remember there was an adder that I added that went over here.
You put it into MAR memory responds at some point, you get the data.
OK, let's take a look at execute.
Execute executes the instruction in add, it performs addition in XOR, it performs bit wise, XOR,
etcetera.
Essentially that happens in the ALU.
Again, add specifies 2 source registers coming from the instruction register based on particular
bits in the instruction register.
Those get connected to the address ports of the register file.
Source register one, source register 2.
So you get both registers out and then perform the add operation using a control signal that says
AL, you should do add because I'm executing an add.
We will see all of these more later on, but that's the execute phase.
And finally the last phase of store result, which writes the result into the designated destination.
Once store result is complete, a new instruction cycle starts with the fetch face.
So store result, for example, add loads alu result into destination register.
How do you do that?
The result of the add happens is over here.
You gate it to this wire and you put it back into the register file specified by the destination
register address that's coming from the instruction register over here.
Some bits in the instruction register specify which register you put the the data into.
Again, this is going to be demystified even more later if you do LDR.
If you have loads register then you put you take the data that's in the MDR, you place them to the
destination register.
OK, so you can use the same components for executing different instructions, but of course you need
to have all components to execute all instructions specified by the ISA.
So that's our instruction cycle.
What we have not talked about is changing the sequence of execution you execute first instruction,
second instruction, third instruction, unless we change the sequence of execution.
So control instructions are critically important because they allow conditional constructs, right?
They allow a program to execute out of sequence.
They can change the PC by loading it during the execute phase.
So what does this do?
That wipes out the incremented PC that is loaded during the fetch phase with something else and
loads with something else.
So let's take a look at jump.
This unconditional branch or unconditional jump, it happens to be specified this way.
Jump change the programme counter to the contents of the base register.
That's the idea.
Is it an up code?
It is a base register.
Everything else is zeroes over here in the encoding and PC gets the data value that's inside the
register identified by base register.
This is called register addressing mode.
As we will see, there are other variations of this that I'm not going to talk about right now.
Jump in MIPS also exists.
There's an unconditional branch, unconditional jump.
This happens when you want to jump to some other part of the program, right?
And we will see in program execution.
So for example, if you're doing some, you're, you're going from some function to another function.
Let me finish this and then we'll be done.
In MIPS, you have a jump target.
It looks like this.
Again, we're going to cover this tomorrow.
It's calculated like this.
It uses some other addressing mode.
So let me look at the LC3 implementation very quickly.
Essentially jump loads SR1 into PC.
You take the value in SR1 and place it into the program counter.
So you need to provide the data path elements to load the PC with a register as opposed to all just
incrementing the PC.
So you have PC gets PC Plus one in the fetch cycle fetch phase, but it gets the value in SR1 in the
execute phase of jump.
OK.
So we're going to start from here tomorrow.
We're going to go into a little bit more detail in the instructions.
Hopefully a lot of these things will be reinforced tomorrow a little bit more.
OK, see you tomorrow.